Exercise 10-5. Tense and lax vowel exercise. Let's practice tense and lax
vowels in context. The intonation is marked for you. When in doubt, try to
leave out the lax vowel rather than run the risk of overpronouncing it. Lip in
place of lip, so it doesn't sound like leap. Repeat. One. Eat. It. I eat it. Two.
Beat. Bit. The beat is a bit strong. 3. Keys. Kiss. Give me a kiss for the keys.
4. Cheek. Chick. The chick's cheek is soft. 5. Deed. Did. He did the deed. 6.
Feet. Fit. These shoes fit my feet. 7. Feel. Fill. Do you feel that we should
feel it? 8. Green. Grin. The Martian's grin was green. 9. Heat. Hit. Last summer
the heat hit hard. 10. Heel. Hill. Put your heel on the hill. 11. Jeep. Jill.
Jill's Jeep is here. 12. Creep. Crypt. Let's creep near the crypt. Thirteen,
leap, lip. He bumped his lip when he leaped. Fourteen, meal, mill. She had a
meal at the mill. Fifteen, neat, knit. He can knit neatly. Sixteen, peel, pill.
Don't peel that pill. Seventeen, read, rid. the reed. 18. Seek, sick. We seek the
sixth sick sheik's sheep. 19. Sheep, ship. There's sheep on the ship. 20. Sleep,
slip. The girl sleeps in a slip. 21. Steal, still. He still 22. Streep. Strip.
Meryl Streep is in a comic strip. 23. Team. Tim. Tim is on the team. 24. These.
This. These are better than this one. 25. Thief. Thing. The thief took my thing. 26.
Weep. Whip. Who weeps from the whips?